<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-27T00:23:46-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Bible as Literature</title><subtitle>Comments, thoughts, criticisms? Drop us a line at TheBibleAsLiteratureYT@gmail.com </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Holy Spirit in Psalm 133</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Holy Spirit in Psalm 133" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133.html"><![CDATA[<p>Psalm 133</p>

<p>1 Behold, how good and how pleasant it is
For brothers to live together in unity!
2 It is like the precious oil on the head,
Running down upon the beard,
As on Aaron’s beard,
The oil which ran down upon the edge of his robes.
3 It is like the dew of Hermon
Coming down upon the mountains of Zion;
For the Lord commanded the blessing there—life forever.</p>

<p>We present an analysis on a beautiful psalm of David, Psalm 133.</p>

<p>The psalm opens with a “behold” inviting us to observe what follows; the delight and goodness of brothers living together in unity. Two images are then given which explain and elaborate this initial exclamation.</p>

<p>Let’s first take a look at these two images as they naturally explain the opening maxim. The first image we have is that of oil. David describes its path. The oil starts at the head, and down the beard; at this point the first high priest of Israel, Aaron, is mentioned as the recipient of this anointing. It continues down the beard and even to the edges of his robe, namely the fine linen garment of the high priesthood [Exodus 28:4-5]. This conjures an image of saturation, abundance, there is no lack of anointing oil on Aaron.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/example.png" alt="My image Name" /></p>

<p>The imagery shifts to that of dew, creating an implicit comparison of abundance of oil to that of the abundance of dew on Mount Hermon. Mount Hermon is a notable mountain at the northern boundary of the promised land, and is an especially fertile spot in an arid climate. However, David imagines this dew as on Mount Zion, the mountain on which Jerusalem is built and is sacred to the Israelites.</p>

<p>Mount Zion is the place where to Lord acts; this dew is subsumed in the blessing of the Lord; life-giving dew, dew as part of a blessing that includes life never-ceasing.</p>

<p>This psalm makes no less than three references to the Holy Spirit, and the concept of the Holy Spirit indeed unifies the psalm. The psalm begins speaking of the unity of brothers. Such a unity is possible only through the Holy Spirit. Indeed, there is no stronger unity than having a common spirit. Paul tells us to “preserve the unity of the Spirit” [Ephesians 4:3].</p>

<p>The anointing oil itself is also synonymous with the Holy Spirit. When both David and Saul are anointed for the kingship, the Bible talks of “the Spirit of the Lord coming mightily” upon them [1 Samuel 10:1,6,10; 16:13, see also Isaiah 61:1]  In Zechariah, the link between the Holy Spirit and the symbolism of oil is made explicit. Zechariah sees two olive trees with branches; branches that provide oil to a lampstand providing light. When he asks about these things, an angel informs him, “Not by might nor by power, but by My Spirit, says the LORD of hosts. [Zechariah 4:4-6]”</p>

<p>Oil, a product of olives, also implies the  agricultural abundance of the promised land, as seen in the oft-used Biblical triad of grain, new wine, and oil, promised in Deuteronomy 7:13. This concept of agricultural abundance unifies the images of oil with the subsequent image of dew, the cause of life from the soil.</p>

<p>The dew of mount hermon is seen as life giving, as is water in an arid desert. Jesus himself uses such an image while standing in the temple, itself a Johanian allusion to Ezekiel, when he states ”He who believes in me, as the Scripture said, From his innermost being will flow rivers of living water.” John then explains  Jesus’ words in the following verse, saying “But this He spoke of the Spirit, who those who believed in Him were to receive . . . ” [John 7:38-39].  Jesus, standing in the temple, made this statement; likewise, in Ezekiel 47, in Ezekiel’s vision of the new temple, a stream of water comes up from the threshold of the temple, widening into a river, giving new life throughout the desert, even to the dead sea. Yes, the DEAD sea, is given new life. The link between the dew, the life-giving water of Mount Hermon in the desert, and the Spirit, the life-giving water of the temple, also in the midst of a desert, is apparent. This further explains why David imagines this dew as on Mt Zion, as this is where the Lord’s temple, and therefore his presence, his Spirit, was to be located.</p>

<p>It is also remarkable that the agricultural abundance is implied via dew, not rain. Elijah, for example, prayed for rain [1 Kings 18:41-45], not dew; nevertheless, here, dew is mentioned. Remember, the garden of Eden was watered with dew [Genesis 2:6], before the rains of the flood. This image of dew thus invokes a reminiscence of the garden of Eden, where man dwelled with God in his presence [Genesis 3:8]. This garden-of-Eden imagery appears often in Scripture, with Ezekiel, again, as a prime example. As God’s presence is associated with the garden of Eden, in which he walked with Adam, God’s presence is necessarily associated with every temple in the Bible, whether Solomon’s or Zerubabbel’s or Ezekiel’s future temple, indeed, the purpose of the temple of God is God’s presence. The latest and best iteration of God’s presence among man, at least so far, is the indwelling of the Holy Spirit in the temple of our bodies [1 Corinthians 6:19], thus restoring the fellowship at the garden of Eden and bringing us  new life [John 3:3, 2 Corinthians 5:17]. The mention of dew, redolent of the garden of Eden, thus reiterates the concept of God’s presence and the life-giving power of the Holy Spirit already displayed in the image of the anointing oil on Aaron.</p>

<p>Finally, Aaron being mentioned as the recipient of the anointing, as opposed to say, David, is also apt. Christ, as our high priest, ushers in the presence of the Holy Spirit just as Aaron’s mediation ushered in the presence of God on the bronze altar, while his continued service allowed for the continuance of God’s presence among the people of Israel [Leviticus 8-9]. [notice the link to Eden and the Holy Spirit?] Futhermore, in a borderline unfathomable statement, Hebrews tells us that Christ, our high priest, is not ashamed to call us brothers as both He, and his people, that is, Christians, both have God as their Father [Hebrew 2:11].</p>

<p>With the preceding discussion in mind, the stated blessing of the Lord, that of life everlasting, follows most naturally. The curse of sin at the garden of Eden was death, death as equatable to separation from God, and, inevitably, with fellow man. The blessing of the Holy Spirit reverses this death, bringing renewal to not only humanity, but indeed all creation [Romans 8:19-21]. This life is necessarily accompanied by the restored presence of God as brought about by none other than the focus of this psalm, the Holy Spirit, taking residence in the redeemed Christian. This life also brings us back to the beginning of the psalm. This is the abundant, communion-with-God-and-with-each-other, type of life, cemented with the unity of the Holy Spirit, this is the life that is so good and delightful. This is the life which David foresaw and so succinctly, yet so vividly, describes for us in these three verses.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Psalm 133]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christ in the Peace Offering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christ in the Peace Offering" /><published>2024-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay.html"><![CDATA[<p>The peace offering, or wholeness offering, was one of the sacrifices of the ancient Israelites. It represented fellowship with God and with one another, and should be considered the communion of the Old Testament. After an animal was slaughtered, the fat and entrails, simultaneously representing the best part of the animal and the seat of emotions of the offerer, were given to God by being burned on the bronze altar. The rest of the sacrifice, minus the priest’s share, could be eaten by the offerer with others, including his friends and family. In this way God and man were able to share something of a meal together, and the animal gave its life to physically sustain the offerer. While the parallel with communion and Jesus’ sacrifice for us are hopefully apparent, we’re here to elaborate on a little-discussed peculiarity of the peace offering, specifically as to when it could be eaten and the typology of this in particular.</p>

<p>Now the peace offering could be eaten, could sustain the person who brought it for one or two days depending on the circumstance. If it was an offering of Thanksgiving, it had to be eaten in one day. In addition, the thanksgivinig offering also had to be accompanied by cooked grain offerings.</p>

<p>If the offering was a freewill offering or an offering marking the fulfillment of a vow, often called a “votive offering”, the offerer had two days to eat the sacrifice.</p>

<p>On the third day, regardless of the type of peace offering, the meat could not be eaten but was considered rotten, impure, offensive, and had to be burned.</p>

<p>Lets explore the reasoning behind this. There are various practical considerations. For example, if the offering was a freewill offering, it might be assumed to be more spontaneous, and the offerer needed more time  to finish the meal. Thus he was given two days to do so. Conversely, limiting the time to consume a thanksgiving offering to one day would perhaps encourage an offerer to share with others, encouraging generosity. And, of course, the most obvious reason as to why three-day-old meat should not be eaten is that it could make the offerer sick. These are all perfectly plausible explanations. However, taking into account other Biblical passages, corresponding theological implications become apparent, and these will be considered here.</p>

<p>God’s commandments in gathering and eating manna for the nation of Israel in Exodus parallels the pattern of the peace offering.  On a normal day of the week, enough mana was collected to be eaten that day. Any manna saved until the next day would spoil; tomorrow was forced to worry about itself. This matches the thanksgiving form of the peace offering, it must be consumed that day. Futhermore, for the thanksgiving peace offering, a grain offering, in the form of cakes and wafers, must also be presented. Grain was the fruit of man’s labor (cf God’s words in the Garden of Eden), and Israel was to be thankful to God as their ultimate provider. Such a concept is also clear in the daily gathering of manna. God provided manna daily, but, in this case, this blessing was nevertheless a harmonizationThis corresponds both to eating previously gathered manna on the Sabbath as well as eating the meat of the votive peace offering the second day. of God’s provision and man’s obedience and effort in gathering. This concept is represented in the grain offering presented with the thanksgiving version of the peace offering.</p>

<p>Likewise, on the day before the Sabbath, enough manna was gathered to be eaten that day and the next day, that is, the Sabbath, when no one could work (quote John). This parallels the votive type of peace offering, given in fulfillment of a vow, which could be eaten the day of, as well as the next day. The principles of gathering manna and the votive offering also parallel in this case. In regards to manna, the people could not rely on their own efforts for the Sabbath; no amount of work could feed them that day, God must be trusted that the previous days’ manna would not spoil. This is likewise true of the votive offering. Vows were made in cases where man trusted God to provide what he could not. An example of such an offering is that of Hannah in regards to the birth of her son, Samuel; she trusted God to provide her a son; such a thing was far outside the bounds of man’s ability. In fulfillment of her vow, she presented animals at the tabernacle after Samuel was born; this was a votive peace offering. As no effort of man could provide manna on the Sabbath, when there was none to collect, the votive offering was eaten on the day it was offered and the second day; signifying only something God could provide.</p>

<p>In regards to his death and resurrection, Jesus likewise appears to draw upon this concept of doing God’s work when appropriate as well as ceasing from labor in accordance with trusting God. Before healing the blind man in John 9 Jesus states, “We must work the work of Him who sent Me as long as it is day; night is coming when no one can work.” Throughout the book of John, Jesus often cryptically refers to his death, as is the case here.  It is no accident that the full day Jesus spent in the grave is the Sabbath, “when no one can work.” While the disciples trusted, obeyed and learned from Jesus when he was alive, the day he was in the grave no one had the ability to do anything, all they could do was trust in what Jesus had told them in the upper room. This corresponds both to eating previously gathered manna on the Sabbath as well as eating the meat of the votive peace offering on the second day.</p>

<p>But now we come to the third day of the peace offering, of gathering manna, and, most importantly, the day of Jesus’ resurrection. Here parallels end and beautiful contrasts begin. Manna could not sustain on the third day, it is not even mentioned; likewise, the meat of the peace offering must be burned to prevent decay, otherwise it would turn putrid. Instead, we turn to something greater, the peace offering of Jesus Christ; his body is true food, and his blood is real drink, the symbolism made clear in communion. On the third day, instead of rotting, God did not, as David states, let Jesus’ body see decay, but his body, the sacrifice, was renewed, resurrected. The communion meal is instead available for all time being able to be taken again and again for all eternity, offering real, permanent nourishment.</p>

<p>Christianity, Kierkegaard states, makes all things new; here, this concept is most literal. Remember, types of Christ not only demonstrate aspects of Christ and his atonement, but also Christ’s superiority to those types’ shortcomings.  It is no different here; with the image, the type, the shadow, the sacrificial meat becomes rotten on the third day. In Christ, the sacrifice not only does not decay, but raises again, renewed, putting on immortality. The contrast could not be greater.  We in turn can partake in the nourishment of Christ, symbolized in communion, again and again. Indeed, this is necessary, as Jesus tells his disciples they, the branches, must abide in him, the true vine; apart from him they, and us, can do nothing. The author of Hebrews likewise echoes such a concept, telling us Christ is “able to save forever those who draw near to God through Him, since He always lives to make intercession for them.” Christ’s nourishment sustains eternally, far past the second day of the peace offering.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The peace offering, or wholeness offering, was one of the sacrifices of the ancient Israelites. It represented fellowship with God and with one another, and should be considered the communion of the Old Testament. After an animal was slaughtered, the fat and entrails, simultaneously representing the best part of the animal and the seat of emotions of the offerer, were given to God by being burned on the bronze altar. The rest of the sacrifice, minus the priest’s share, could be eaten by the offerer with others, including his friends and family. In this way God and man were able to share something of a meal together, and the animal gave its life to physically sustain the offerer. While the parallel with communion and Jesus’ sacrifice for us are hopefully apparent, we’re here to elaborate on a little-discussed peculiarity of the peace offering, specifically as to when it could be eaten and the typology of this in particular.]]></summary></entry></feed>