<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-30T23:30:09-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Bible as Literature</title><subtitle>Comments, thoughts, criticisms? Drop us a line at TheBibleAsLiteratureYT@gmail.com </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Serpent.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman" /><published>2024-04-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Serpent</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/28/Serpent.html"><![CDATA[<p>The image of the serpent, Leviathan, the dragon, is ubiquitous in Scripture, mentioned at the beginning of Genesis, the end of Revelation, and many places in between, such as the well-known example in Job. John, in Revelation, is clear: “the dragon, the serpent of old” is the devil, also known as Satan (Revelation 20:2).</p>

<p>This analysis serves as an introduction to the concept of the serpent, aka the dragon, and the role he plays in antagonizing God’s people, while also inadvertently bringing about God’s purposes. Here, we will specifically focus on his and his offspring’s role in the story Genesis. The Bible introduces this character in Genesis 3 with the fall of man, and this is where we will start.</p>

<p>After Adam and Eve, enticed by the serpent, ate of the tree of which they were not to eat, the tree of knowledge of good and evil, sin entered the world and death through sin (Romans 5:12). Creation was cursed, the work of man’s hands became toilsome and the pain of childbirth multiplied greatly for the woman, who was also to live in subjugation to her husband (Genesis 3:16-17). The serpent was also cursed, and in this curse was the first prophecy of Jesus Christ and God’s promise to redeem mankind. God states to the serpent (Genesis 3:14-15), 
“Because you have done this, cursed are you more than all cattle, and more than every beast of the field; on your belly you will go, and dust you will eat all the days of your life; and I will put enmity between you and the woman, and between your seed and her seed; he shall bruise you on the head, and you shall bruise him on the heel.”</p>

<p>Let’s examine this text: the serpent is cursed in the sense of being the lowest of the low. Being “on his belly,” “eating dust” defines the curse.  This describes his proximity to the ground, such that the serpent is lower than any other animal. Furthermore, at stated by God, there is destined to be animosity not only between the serpent and the woman, as was the case in the serpent’s deception of the woman in the garden, but there would also be animosity between the seed, or offspring, of the serpent and the offspring of the woman. Notice, the serpent, not only the woman, has offspring. This animosity ignites fighting between the two seeds out of which the offspring of the woman will ultimately emerge victorious. The serpent’s head is bruised, or “crushed” in some translations. The concept portrayed is that of a fatal wound. While this victory will be most decisive, it will not come without battle scars. However, the serpent will merely strike the offspring of the woman’s heel. <br />
This passage is famously and correctly known as the first prophecy of Jesus Christ. The victory of the seed of the woman refers to Christ’s messiahship and his defeat of Satan. However, much more can be garnered from these two verses. Indeed, this prophecy not only informs our reading of the book of Genesis, but gives us a firmer grasp on the message of the entire Bible. The relevance of this prophecy throughout the book of Genesis is what we will discuss here. Nevertheless, this theme is present in various parts of the Bible, in books such as Exodus, Judges, Job and the gospels.</p>

<p>Further examining the text, the serpent is cursed to crawl on his belly and eat dust, the very substance to which man returns upon death. The serpent is destined to eat dust, that is, to work for the death of mankind, this is his food. However, out of Eve’s own body, that is, from mankind itself, will come a conqueror, one to crush the serpent’s head, undoing the curse of death for which the serpent works. In this regard, an ensuing battle is most natural.  As this promised conqueror will be Eve’s son, or at least her descendent, we have a son of the promise (compare Galatians 4:28) at the beginning of Genesis. The term “son of the promise” and the “seed of the woman” will be used almost interchangeably in this analysis.</p>

<p>Now the serpent works for man’s death by inciting disobedience to God, one might say disobedience to God is equatable with death. As such, the serpent works contrary to God’s commands. This contrarian stance is necessarily bound up with purely human will and desires. Indeed, this is what the serpent appeals to in his deception, the exaltation of man: he told Eve that by eating the fruit she would “be like God” (Genesis 3:5)</p>

<p>It is also worth noting that the mention of enmity in the prophecy plays a central role in the unfolding of Genesis. The godly offspring of the promise is generally presented in the position of the literary protagonist, while the seed of the serpent in the corresponding role of antagonist, pitted against the offspring of the promise.</p>

<p>Such is immediately clear in the story of Cain and Abel. We have conflict between an older brother who’s offering to God, that of crops, was not accepted, and a younger brother, whose offering, that of sheep, was accepted. The murder of Abel by Cain demonstrates the enmity between the two. As punishment, Cain is cursed to the life of a wanderer and banished to the east.</p>

<p>In this story we also have an introduction into the dichotomy of man’s failed effort vs God’s grace, aspects that always characterize the seed of the serpent and seed of the woman, respectively. Cain’s offering was that of crops (Genesis 4:3), the produce of the ground for which man labors. This labor was cursed after the fall (Genesis 3:16-17) with the ground now producing “thorns and thistles” in addition to food. Cain offers to God this cursed work of his hands. Such an offering could never be acceptable. Abel, however, offers the “firstlings of his flocks” (Genesis 4:4). Fast-forwarding a bit in Genesis, God states after the flood, “ . . . everything that creeps on the ground, and all the fish of the sea, into your hand they are given. Every moving thing that is alive shall be food for you; I give all to you, as I gave the green plant.” (Genesis 9:2-3). In the context of the fall, crops are considered the work of man’s hands while animals are a gift of God, not part of the original plan of creation. This is evident in the animal skins God uses to cover Adam and Eve’s nakedness after the fall (Genesis 3:21). Their clothing, an act of God’s grace, came through the death of animals, a death only introduced after sin.  In this way Abel’s offering of his flocks, which are a gift of God, accord with God’s grace, standing in contrast to Cain and the work of his hands. The dual genealogies that follow in Genesis chapters 4 and 5 further expound on the casting of Cain as the offspring of the serpent. One presents the line of Cain, the other the line of Seth, the son of Adam and Eve that was to replace Abel in the role of the son of the promise.</p>

<p>The line of Cain consummates in the character of Lamech, who takes two wives, gloats over killing, and promises vengeance on his enemies. (Genesis 4:19-24) The corresponding lineage of Seth includes the character of Enoch, who walked with God (Genesis 5:22) and was a prophet as mentioned by Jude (Jude 14-15), and ends in the godly man of Noah, renowned for his obedience to God in building the ark and whose name means “rest.” The contrast between the two lineages is clear.</p>

<p>Further examination of the names and structure of these two lineages reveals additional insight. Even a cursory reading will reveal phonetic similarities, if not exact matches, between the various names in the two lineages, such as Kenan and Cain.  Matching up the genealogies name by name from the text, and filling in Adam as the father of Cain, we have a distinctive pattern as shown (see “Lineages” diagram). While “Adam” and “Enosh” are not phonetically similar, Adam is a literal word for “man” in Hebrew, while Enosh also means “man,” but with an emphasis on his mortal aspect. While not phonetically similar, this nevertheless showcases the parallel between the two names. The phonetic similarities or matches of all other names is also clear. The pattern naturally draws focus to the names of Irad and Jared. While the meaning of all names in these two genealogies is worth an in-depth study and is highly encouraged, we discuss the names of the progenitors, Cain and Seth, and the focal point of the pattern, that of Irad and Jared.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/lineages.PNG" alt="lineages" /></p>

<p>First, we recall the birth of Cain. After Eve gives birth to Cain, she makes the statement, “I have gotten a manchild with the help of the Lord.” (Genesis 4:1) Despite the clunkiness of the NASB translation, in light of this statement, Cain’s name is appropriate, as it means “acquired.” Eve had been driven out of the garden of Eden, separated from God into cursed creation.  She, no doubt, desires to return. With a promise from God that her offspring would bring such a salvation about, it makes sense that Eve would long for a son. It appears she sees Cain as a goal fulfilled, saying “I have acquired a son,” with expectation that God would bring about salvation through him. Unfortunately, Eve was mistaken; Cain turned out to be a murderer with his offspring only compounding his sins.</p>

<p>Now consider the birth of Seth. Seth not only contrasts with Cain in the worthiness of his offspring, in that of Noah and others, but in his very name. “Seth,” means “to give” or “to set,” therefore “to appoint.”  Through Cain, Eve attempted to “acquire” the promise on her own, while God’s sovereignty nevertheless “appointed” the promise through Seth. It should come as no surprise that the birth of Cain, corresponding to humanity’s choice, resulted in murder and general disaster, while the birth of Seth, corresponding to God’s appointment, resulted in men calling on the name of the Lord (Genesis 4:26).</p>

<p>This examination of names of Cain and Seth helps further explain the focal point of the pattern found in the parallel genealogies, that of Irad and Jared. The meaning of “Irad,” in Hebrew, suggests the concept of a city while also being the word from which another Hebrew word, meaning “wild donkey” is derived. The meaning of “city” is quite fitting given the reputation of Cain’s line, considering the city he built, perhaps in rebellion, after being cursed by God to forever be a wanderer (Genesis 4:12), and also in the light of the tower of Babel, discussed later, and the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah to the east of the promised land.  However, we will focus on the second meaning here, that of “wild donkey.” In light of the story cycles still to be discussed, the name of Irad appears to be something of a foil to that of Jared, which means “to descend,” having the connotation of losing prominence and being humbled. With the name of Irad, we have something untamed and wild, perhaps rebellious. With the name of Jared, we have the idea of being brought low in humility, submission, and obedience.</p>

<p>From simply the names and peripheral circumstances of these two genealogies, we are introduced to the archetypal pattern that will encapsulate all subsequent story cycles in Genesis. The antagonist, the seed of the serpent, will have a rebellious, self-serving will, that is somewhat degraded and on par with a beast, usually a donkey. The seed of the serpent usually appears more impressive in regard to man’s metrics, most often shown in that he is the firstborn, which was a significant advantage in the ancient near east. The character of the serpent’s seed is synonymous with human effort and its results, in much the same way that “Cain” means “acquired” and “Irad” represents an untamed donkey.  The seed of the woman, God’s promise of redemption, is, in contrast, humble, or at least eventually humbled by his circumstances and ultimately God. Being the seed of God’s promise, the seed of the woman is necessarily chosen by God’s sovereign will and is therefore often lacking in the eyes of man. This again, is generally shown in the birth order of the seed of the woman, who is never the firstborn. The lack of commendation from man ensures that God is working, not man, in the life of his chosen ones. These concepts are succinctly captured in the opposing name pairs of “Cain” and “Irad”, “Jared” and “Seth”.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/cain_abel.PNG" alt="cain_abel" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/nimrod_abraham.PNG" alt="nimrod_abraham" /></p>

<p>Nimrod/Abraham</p>

<p>After the flood, two related but opposing narratives are presented. The first of that is Nimrod, a “mighty hunter” (Genesis 10:9) whose name means “rebellion;” he establishes the kingdom of Babel, also known as Babylon, Babel being similar to the Hebrew word for “confuse”. He settles in the East in Shinar in sympathy with the likes of Cain, who settled east of Eden in the land of Nod. Here Genesis relates the tower of Babel narrative. Mankind attempts to build a tower to reach heaven and make a name for itself, effectively trying to transgress the boundary set between God and man via the rainbow after the flood.  God, that is, YHWH, comes down and frustrates this plan, by confusing man’s language and scattering him throughout the earth. In contrast to Nimrod’s failed human efforts with the tower of Babel in the east, God calls Abraham from Ur and promises to establish him in a land in the west. God says to Abraham, “Go forth from your country . . . to the land which I will show you . . . I will make you a great nation, And I will bless you, And make your name great . . . ”(Genesis 12:2). God’s promise of making Abraham’s name great showcases a prominent literary contrast.  When building the tower of Babel, the men of the earth say to each other “let us make for ourselves a name (shem).” (Genesis 11:4). Immediately after the tower of Babel narrative, Genesis records the lineage of the man Shem, “Shem” being the Hebrew word for the English word “name.” This line ends with Abraham, and God promises to make Abraham’s  “name (shem)” great, the very goal the men of the earth sought through the tower of Babel. God’s choice via his promises guaranteed Abraham’s future prosperity and fame in stark contrast to man’s failed efforts.</p>

<p>Secondly, it is important to note that God’s promises to Abraham overlap the promised victory over the serpent. You might say one subsumes the other. That is, God’s fulfilling his promises to Abraham includes the defeat of the serpent. Recall the last part of God’s promise to Abraham, “In you all the families of the earth will be blessed.” (Genesis 12:3). As all of mankind was cursed via the fall, all of mankind would be blessed through Abraham. Through Abraham would come the undoing of the curse of the garden, the defeat of the serpent. 
As a final observation of the Nimrod and Abraham pairing, it is important to note that each is the beginning of a nation that play a major role in Biblical history. Israel is, of course, central to the Bible and Abraham is her father.  Nimrod establishes Babylon, the country that destroys Jerusalem and sends her into exile. Furthermore, Nimrod is a hunter, while the nation of Israel is to be a nation of shepherds. Shepherds, in contrast to hunting wild animals, are to care for their obedient and trusting flocks (1 Samuel 17:34-35, John 10:1-18). Thus, Nimrod and Abraham, as offspring of the serpent and the woman, respectively, fit opposing roles as well as the antagonistic prediction of the garden of Eden prophecy.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/ishmael_isaac.PNG" alt="Ishmael_Isaac" /></p>

<p>Ishmael/Isaac</p>

<p>As necessary to fulfill his promises to Abraham in making him into a great nation, God promises Abraham a son who will be born via Sarah, although she was past the age of childbearing and barren (Genesis 18:10-11). Thus we have a repetition of the theme of a son of promise. But, in concert with the pattern of Genesis, the son of God’s promise will nevertheless be set in enmity with the seed of the serpent, corresponding to man’s efforts. Abraham’s son by his slave women Hagar fills this antagonist role in the character of Ishmael.  Notice it is human effort that leads to birth of Ishmael; Sarah, impatient for her promised son, directs Abraham to obtain a son for her through Hagar. This effort is successful only to the extent that an actual son is born. Thus, typical of serpent-like thinking, Sarah and Abraham try to obtain God’s promise by their own efforts. Not surprisingly, conflict arises between Ishmael and Isaac. When Isaac is weaned, Abraham puts on a great feast. However, Ishmael is found mocking at this celebration (Genesis 21:9) and Sara drives Hagar and Ishmael out of Abraham’s household into the desert.</p>

<p>Ishmael being cast as the seed of the serpent is perhaps most clear in Genesis 16:12, when the Lord tells Hagar what her son will be like. God states, “He will be a wild donkey of a man, His hand will be against everyone, and everyone’s hand will be against him; And he will live to the east of all his brothers.” Notice the common themes: his untamed nature corresponding to the genealogy of Cain, and the name “Irad” in particular; he will settle in the east like Cain and Nimrod; finally, animosity will exist between him and everyone else.</p>

<p>Later in Abraham’s story cycle, we learn that Ishmael “lived in the wilderness and became an archer” (Genesis 21:20). This links him with Nimrod, the “mighty hunter” and, later, Esau, who hunts with bow and arrow. (Genesis 27:3) It is remarkable that the arrow is linked with poison and deceit in the Bible. Jeremiah states of evildoers in Israel, saying “Their tongue is a deadly arrow, it speaks deceit . . .” and also, “They bend their tongue like a bow, lies and not truth prevail . . . ” (Jeremiah 9:3,8, also see Psalm 64 for a clear reference to this idea).  Job in turn attributes poison arrows to the Almighty, ignorant that their more direct origin was Satan, the accuser. (Job 6:4, Job 1-2). Thus we have the idea of a deceitful mouth full of poison, a clear reference to the serpent in the garden of Eden. It is perhaps this idea James has in mind when he calls the tongue “a restless evil, full of deadly poison” and Paul also when he mentions “flaming arrows of the evil one.” (James 3:8, Ephesians 6:16)</p>

<p>Contrary to Ishmael’s defiant nature, Isaac is at the center of one of the greatest acts of humility in all of Genesis.  In Genesis 22, God commands Abraham to offer his son as a burnt offering on Mount Moriah. Abraham obeys to the point of raising the knife to slay Isaac, and Isaac does not resist. An angel prevents Abraham from following all the way through, but his heart is nonetheless fully obedient. This story shows Abraham’s growth of faith, from trying to force God’s promise through Ishmael to fully obeying a command that seems to contradict this promise. Likewise, Isaac’s submission to such a brutal act cast him in stark contrast to the belligerent nature of Ishmael. In sympathy with the name “Jared”, Abraham and Isaac are, respectively, humbled, and humble.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/jacob_esau.PNG" alt="jacob_esau" /></p>

<p>Esau/Jacob</p>

<p>Next, we have another pair of brothers in the characters of Jacob and Esau. These brothers fit the seed of the woman/seed of the serpent pattern quite well with God declaring that the older brother, Esau, will serve the younger, Jacob, (Genesis 25:23) despite Esau being their father Isaac’s favorite. (Genesis 25:28). There was enmity between these two brothers from the womb as they “struggled together within” their mother Rebekah (Genesis 25:22), with Esau eventually desiring to kill Jacob (Genesis 27:41) later in life. Esau’s hatred of Jacob was not without reason as Jacob tricked their father into giving him Esau’s blessing of the firstborn (Genesis 27). In this well-known story, Jacob covers himself in goat skins, tricking his nearly blind father into thinking he is the hirsute Esau, as Isaac must rely on his touch to identify his son. Isaac thus unwittingly gives Jacob the irrevocable blessing of the firstborn (Genesis 27:33). After Jacob’s deception is made known, Esau nevertheless begs for a blessing from Isaac (Genesis 27:38). Isaac complies, but the “blessing” sounds more like a curse. Genesis records the respective blessings Isaac gives Jacob and Esau, and each in turn highlights their roles as the seed of the woman and the seed of the serpent. In Genesis 27:27-28 Isaac says to Jacob, “See, the smell of my son is like the smell of a field which the LORD has blessed; Now may God give you of the dew of heaven, and of the fatness of the earth, and an abundance of grain and new wine.” This blessing of unfettered agricultural prosperity as well as dew is reminiscent of the garden of Eden and is in accordance with the seed of woman’s victory. Namely, the undoing of the curse of thorns and thistles.</p>

<p>Esau’s not-so-great “blessing” stands in stark contrast to this. Isaac says, “Behold, away from the fertility of the earth shall be your dwelling, and away from the dew of heaven from above. By your sword you shall live, and your brother you shall serve; but it shall come about when you become restless, that you will break his yoke from your neck.” (Genesis 27:39-40). This blessing is in accordance with Cain’s banishment to the east of Eden, that is, the fertility of the earth, and Ishmael’s animosity toward everyone. Esau is cursed to the role of a rebellious plow animal also in sympathy with Ishmael, the “wild donkey of a man,” and the previously discussed name of Irad. The dual mention of Esau’s hairiness, both at birth and later in life, compounds this beastly image (Genesis 25:25, 27:11). Finally, as previously discussed, Esau is both a hunter and archer (Genesis 27:3), further linking him to Nimrod and Ishmael. Esau’s role as the seed of the serpent is clear.</p>

<p>Fulfilling the role of the seed of the woman, we now turn to the humbling of Jacob. On the night of Jacob’s fated reunion with a potentially hostile Esau, Jacob wrestles with God, incarnate in the body of a man. (Genesis 32). Jacob’s dread of Esau, as well as the wrestling match, portray Jacob in a lowly state before God. That night, Jacob prays, “I am unworthy of all the favor and of all the faithfulness, which You have shown to Your servant” While the man, that is, God incarnate, does not prevail against Jacob after wrestling with him all night, this is apparently by choice. The man ultimately shows his supremacy over Jacob by casually touching his hip, dislocating it. Jacob then grabs hold of the man, demanding the man bless him.  Like Abraham, Jacob realizes human striving, like an hours-long wrestling match, is fruitless outside of God’s purpose. Blessing must come from God. As God is faithful, the man blesses Jacob there.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/brothers_joseph.PNG" alt="brothers_joseph" /></p>

<p>Judah/Joseph</p>

<p>In the final story cycle in Genesis, that of Joseph and his brothers, familiar patterns emerge. We have a sharp conflict between Joseph, whose fancy coat and revelatory dreams incite jealousy in his older brothers.  Again, in sympathy with the donkey-like description of both Ishmael and Esau, and the name of Irad, as well as the deception of the serpent, his brothers deceptively use a false story of a “wild beast” to spite him. They dip Joseph’s coat in goat’s blood telling their father, Jacob, “a wild beast has devoured him.” In reality, the brothers, led by Judah, sell Joseph into slavery and he gets taken to Egypt. (Genesis 37:33, 36)  In contrast to all the brother’s serpent-like qualities, notice Joseph, the youngest character of those in the conflict, is the person God chooses to exalt.</p>

<p>Joseph, the seed of the woman, typical of the Genesis pattern, is humbled by being sold into slavery and eventually thrown in prison. Due to his ability to interpret dreams and wisdom in dealing with the famine that extended to all the known world, Joseph is exalted to second in command of Egypt (Genesis 41). The one God chooses is exalted, this makes sense and shares parallels to the rest of Genesis.  However, the fate of Judah and his brothers, the literary offspring of the serpent, decidedly does not follow the previous story cycles. The seed of the serpent does not languish in punishment and obscurity in some land to the east. Judah, initially the seed of the serpent, is instead humbled and redeemed. Indeed, the action of serpent’s seed was part of God’s plan all along. Joseph states of his brothers’ actions, “You meant evil against me, but God meant it for good . . .” Judah, as leading and representing the rest of his brothers, goes through quite the character arc. From selling his younger brother into slavery at the beginning of the cycle; by the end he volunteers to stay as a captive in Egypt in place of younger brother Benjamin, when it appears Benjamin is guilty of stealing (Genesis 44:33). Judah repents, is forgiven and is reconciled to his former enemy (Genesis 45:15), the promised son, God’s chosen one, Joseph, who saves the world from famine.  The parallel to the salvation message of Jesus Christ, the ultimate son of promise, and fallen, serpent-like mankind, is hopefully clear to the viewer.</p>

<p>Within the antagonistic group of brothers there occurs something of a subplot involving the characters of Reuben, the firstborn of Jacob, and Judah. In the eyes of man, Reuben should hold the place of prominence among the brothers. Reuben attempts to claim such a position, but his plans fail both in his attempt to rescue Joseph and in convincing Jacob to let Benjamin come to Egypt at the demand of Joseph. In both instances, Judah’s plans are the ones that succeed, first in preventing Joseph’s death by selling him into slavery and then in bringing Benjamin to Egypt. Ultimately, it is Judah that catalyzes the reunion of the brothers to Joseph and who receives the right of the firstborn, as we will see in Jacob’s prophecy (Genesis 37:18-36, Genesis 42:36-43:15, 44:18-34). Here, within the thematic element of the offspring of the serpent, we have a nested pattern of man’s failed effort and God’s choice, which is nonetheless a major theme of Genesis. Such a macrocosm-within-the-microcosm structure is remarkably common in Biblical accounts. This pattern-within-a -pattern can also be found in the accounts of Judah’s and Joseph’s sons, thus the pattern gets nested even one level deeper. In both cases the second born is favored ahead of the first (Genesis 38:27-30, 48:17-20, compare David’s statement in 2 Samuel 5:20).</p>

<p>The book of Genesis signs off with the prophecy of Jacob, ushering the reader into the future of God’s redemptive plan for mankind. The inevitable victory of the woman’s offspring is revisited once more. In Genesis 49, Jacob gives a prophecy for each of his twelve sons. Of all Jacob’s sons, Judah, a redeemed sinner, ultimately occupies the central role of the book by being the conduit by which the Messiah, the ultimate son of promise, would come. The redemptive theme, enacted immediately after the fall of mankind, comes to its climax here at the end of Genesis. Jacob tells us that the one who would crush the serpent’s head will come from Judah’s lineage, stating: “Your hand shall be at the neck of you enemies . . . The scepter shall not depart from Judah, nor the ruler’s staff from between his feet, until Shiloh comes, and to him shall be the obedience of the peoples. He ties his foal to the vine, and his donkey’s colt to the choice vine . . . ”  (Genesis 49:8, 10). Remember God’s promises to Abraham, that from him will come a great nation and a blessing for the world. As stated earlier, these promises imply the defeat of the serpent; now, God’s promises toward Abraham are further subsumed in this prophecy; the conqueror and ruler for the nation of Abraham will come through his descendent Judah.  Also, notice again the donkey/beast theme. In accordance with the character arc of Judah, and the “obedience of the peoples,” the donkey becomes tamed, humble, like the son of promise. In fact, Judah is the one that brings this about as he is the one that “ties his foal to the vine.” God shows us the magnificence of his grace by granting it to the redeemed to play a role in bringing about the redeemer. The redemption of Judah brings about the redemption of mankind. (compare to the “great commission,” where the redeemed work for the redemption of others)</p>

<p>But of course, as we should come to expect, right alongside the son of promise comes the seed of the serpent, alluded to in Jacob’s prophecy about Dan.  Jacob states of Dan, “Dan shall be a serpent in the way, a horned snake in the path, that bites the horse’s heels, so that the rider falls backwards.” (Genesis 49:17). This is not to suggest that the tribe of Dan is somehow linked to Satan, although there is some speculation that the antichrist will come from the tribe of Dan (notably, John leaves Dan out of the list of tribes in Revelation), which is possibly at least somewhat linked to this passage. That view is not prescribed here. But, interestingly, the tribe of Dan, in the book of Judges, does show strong serpent-like tendencies.  Whatever the case, as the author of Genesis casts Dan as some type of serpent, juxtaposed with Judah, the son of promise, in the same passage, the book closes with the same literary theme with which it began, and shows Genesis to be a masterfully constructed literary whole. Furthermore, the message of Genesis is that of redemption; God shows grace to those who are “outside the promise”. God is active in the lives of Hagar and Ishmael, for example (Genesis 21:14-21).</p>

<p>As a final observation, we’ll take a look at the cryptic statement Jacob makes after his prophecy about the serpent-like Dan; Jacob prays, ”For your salvation I wait O Lord.” (Genesis 49:18) The immediate context of the statement, the prophecy concerning his sons, offers little insight into this exclamation. However, from within the literary context of Genesis as a whole, the statement almost becomes necessary. Genesis clearly predicts the redemption of mankind immediately after the fall; God declares it. And the characters we meet in Genesis long for this redemption, in one form or another. Eve hoped it would come through her son Cain. Abraham, like Eve, learned patience for God’s promises. Here Jacob, while reunited to his son, now lives outside the promised land in Egypt, away from his inheritance.  With his statement, Jacob shows he has learned this humble patience as well. We could say this is something all God’s followers would do well to learn. Genesis ends happily with Jacob being reunited with Joseph, but mankind remains unredeemed, still living under the curses of the fall. The reader comes to understand that all that has taken place in Genesis is just the beginning of God’s great redemptive plan. Jacob, as a proper servant, resigns himself to wait for God’s salvation from the serpent. A salvation that would only come when Jesus Christ, on the cross, declared, “It is finished.” (John 19:30)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The image of the serpent, Leviathan, the dragon, is ubiquitous in Scripture, mentioned at the beginning of Genesis, the end of Revelation, and many places in between, such as the well-known example in Job. John, in Revelation, is clear: “the dragon, the serpent of old” is the devil, also known as Satan (Revelation 20:2).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Holy Spirit in Psalm 133</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Holy Spirit in Psalm 133" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/15/Psalm133.html"><![CDATA[<p>Psalm 133</p>

<p>1 Behold, how good and how pleasant it is
For brothers to live together in unity!
2 It is like the precious oil on the head,
Running down upon the beard,
As on Aaron’s beard,
The oil which ran down upon the edge of his robes.
3 It is like the dew of Hermon
Coming down upon the mountains of Zion;
For the Lord commanded the blessing there—life forever.</p>

<p>We present an analysis on a beautiful psalm of David, Psalm 133.</p>

<p>The psalm opens with a “behold” inviting us to observe what follows; the delight and goodness of brothers living together in unity. Two images are then given which explain and elaborate this initial exclamation.</p>

<p>Let’s first take a look at these two images as they naturally explain the opening maxim. The first image we have is that of oil. David describes its path. The oil starts at the head, and down the beard; at this point the first high priest of Israel, Aaron, is mentioned as the recipient of this anointing. It continues down the beard and even to the edges of his robe, namely the fine linen garment of the high priesthood [Exodus 28:4-5]. This conjures an image of saturation, abundance, there is no lack of anointing oil on Aaron.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/example.png" alt="My image Name" /></p>

<p>The imagery shifts to that of dew, creating an implicit comparison of abundance of oil to that of the abundance of dew on Mount Hermon. Mount Hermon is a notable mountain at the northern boundary of the promised land, and is an especially fertile spot in an arid climate. However, David imagines this dew as on Mount Zion, the mountain on which Jerusalem is built and is sacred to the Israelites.</p>

<p>Mount Zion is the place where to Lord acts; this dew is subsumed in the blessing of the Lord; life-giving dew, dew as part of a blessing that includes life never-ceasing.</p>

<p>This psalm makes no less than three references to the Holy Spirit, and the concept of the Holy Spirit indeed unifies the psalm. The psalm begins speaking of the unity of brothers. Such a unity is possible only through the Holy Spirit. Indeed, there is no stronger unity than having a common spirit. Paul tells us to “preserve the unity of the Spirit” [Ephesians 4:3].</p>

<p>The anointing oil itself is also synonymous with the Holy Spirit. When both David and Saul are anointed for the kingship, the Bible talks of “the Spirit of the Lord coming mightily” upon them [1 Samuel 10:1,6,10; 16:13, see also Isaiah 61:1]  In Zechariah, the link between the Holy Spirit and the symbolism of oil is made explicit. Zechariah sees two olive trees with branches; branches that provide oil to a lampstand providing light. When he asks about these things, an angel informs him, “Not by might nor by power, but by My Spirit, says the LORD of hosts. [Zechariah 4:4-6]”</p>

<p>Oil, a product of olives, also implies the  agricultural abundance of the promised land, as seen in the oft-used Biblical triad of grain, new wine, and oil, promised in Deuteronomy 7:13. This concept of agricultural abundance unifies the images of oil with the subsequent image of dew, the cause of life from the soil.</p>

<p>The dew of mount hermon is seen as life giving, as is water in an arid desert. Jesus himself uses such an image while standing in the temple, itself a Johanian allusion to Ezekiel, when he states ”He who believes in me, as the Scripture said, From his innermost being will flow rivers of living water.” John then explains  Jesus’ words in the following verse, saying “But this He spoke of the Spirit, who those who believed in Him were to receive . . . ” [John 7:38-39].  Jesus, standing in the temple, made this statement; likewise, in Ezekiel 47, in Ezekiel’s vision of the new temple, a stream of water comes up from the threshold of the temple, widening into a river, giving new life throughout the desert, even to the dead sea. Yes, the DEAD sea, is given new life. The link between the dew, the life-giving water of Mount Hermon in the desert, and the Spirit, the life-giving water of the temple, also in the midst of a desert, is apparent. This further explains why David imagines this dew as on Mt Zion, as this is where the Lord’s temple, and therefore his presence, his Spirit, was to be located.</p>

<p>It is also remarkable that the agricultural abundance is implied via dew, not rain. Elijah, for example, prayed for rain [1 Kings 18:41-45], not dew; nevertheless, here, dew is mentioned. Remember, the garden of Eden was watered with dew [Genesis 2:6], before the rains of the flood. This image of dew thus invokes a reminiscence of the garden of Eden, where man dwelled with God in his presence [Genesis 3:8]. This garden-of-Eden imagery appears often in Scripture, with Ezekiel, again, as a prime example. As God’s presence is associated with the garden of Eden, in which he walked with Adam, God’s presence is necessarily associated with every temple in the Bible, whether Solomon’s or Zerubabbel’s or Ezekiel’s future temple, indeed, the purpose of the temple of God is God’s presence. The latest and best iteration of God’s presence among man, at least so far, is the indwelling of the Holy Spirit in the temple of our bodies [1 Corinthians 6:19], thus restoring the fellowship at the garden of Eden and bringing us  new life [John 3:3, 2 Corinthians 5:17]. The mention of dew, redolent of the garden of Eden, thus reiterates the concept of God’s presence and the life-giving power of the Holy Spirit already displayed in the image of the anointing oil on Aaron.</p>

<p>Finally, Aaron being mentioned as the recipient of the anointing, as opposed to say, David, is also apt. Christ, as our high priest, ushers in the presence of the Holy Spirit just as Aaron’s mediation ushered in the presence of God on the bronze altar, while his continued service allowed for the continuance of God’s presence among the people of Israel [Leviticus 8-9]. [notice the link to Eden and the Holy Spirit?] Futhermore, in a borderline unfathomable statement, Hebrews tells us that Christ, our high priest, is not ashamed to call us brothers as both He, and his people, that is, Christians, both have God as their Father [Hebrew 2:11].</p>

<p>With the preceding discussion in mind, the stated blessing of the Lord, that of life everlasting, follows most naturally. The curse of sin at the garden of Eden was death, death as equatable to separation from God, and, inevitably, with fellow man. The blessing of the Holy Spirit reverses this death, bringing renewal to not only humanity, but indeed all creation [Romans 8:19-21]. This life is necessarily accompanied by the restored presence of God as brought about by none other than the focus of this psalm, the Holy Spirit, taking residence in the redeemed Christian. This life also brings us back to the beginning of the psalm. This is the abundant, communion-with-God-and-with-each-other, type of life, cemented with the unity of the Holy Spirit, this is the life that is so good and delightful. This is the life which David foresaw and so succinctly, yet so vividly, describes for us in these three verses.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Psalm 133]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christ in the Peace Offering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christ in the Peace Offering" /><published>2024-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/03/15/ThirdDay.html"><![CDATA[<p>The peace offering, or wholeness offering, was one of the sacrifices of the ancient Israelites. It represented fellowship with God and with one another, and should be considered the communion of the Old Testament. After an animal was slaughtered, the fat and entrails, simultaneously representing the best part of the animal and the seat of emotions of the offerer, were given to God by being burned on the bronze altar. The rest of the sacrifice, minus the priest’s share, could be eaten by the offerer with others, including his friends and family. In this way God and man were able to share something of a meal together, and the animal gave its life to physically sustain the offerer. While the parallel with communion and Jesus’ sacrifice for us are hopefully apparent, we’re here to elaborate on a little-discussed peculiarity of the peace offering, specifically as to when it could be eaten and the typology of this in particular.</p>

<p>Now the peace offering could be eaten, could sustain the person who brought it for one or two days depending on the circumstance. If it was an offering of Thanksgiving, it had to be eaten in one day. In addition, the thanksgivinig offering also had to be accompanied by cooked grain offerings.</p>

<p>If the offering was a freewill offering or an offering marking the fulfillment of a vow, often called a “votive offering”, the offerer had two days to eat the sacrifice.</p>

<p>On the third day, regardless of the type of peace offering, the meat could not be eaten but was considered rotten, impure, offensive, and had to be burned.</p>

<p>Lets explore the reasoning behind this. There are various practical considerations. For example, if the offering was a freewill offering, it might be assumed to be more spontaneous, and the offerer needed more time  to finish the meal. Thus he was given two days to do so. Conversely, limiting the time to consume a thanksgiving offering to one day would perhaps encourage an offerer to share with others, encouraging generosity. And, of course, the most obvious reason as to why three-day-old meat should not be eaten is that it could make the offerer sick. These are all perfectly plausible explanations. However, taking into account other Biblical passages, corresponding theological implications become apparent, and these will be considered here.</p>

<p>God’s commandments in gathering and eating manna for the nation of Israel in Exodus parallels the pattern of the peace offering.  On a normal day of the week, enough mana was collected to be eaten that day. Any manna saved until the next day would spoil; tomorrow was forced to worry about itself. This matches the thanksgiving form of the peace offering, it must be consumed that day. Futhermore, for the thanksgiving peace offering, a grain offering, in the form of cakes and wafers, must also be presented. Grain was the fruit of man’s labor (cf God’s words in the Garden of Eden), and Israel was to be thankful to God as their ultimate provider. Such a concept is also clear in the daily gathering of manna. God provided manna daily, but, in this case, this blessing was nevertheless a harmonizationThis corresponds both to eating previously gathered manna on the Sabbath as well as eating the meat of the votive peace offering the second day. of God’s provision and man’s obedience and effort in gathering. This concept is represented in the grain offering presented with the thanksgiving version of the peace offering.</p>

<p>Likewise, on the day before the Sabbath, enough manna was gathered to be eaten that day and the next day, that is, the Sabbath, when no one could work (quote John). This parallels the votive type of peace offering, given in fulfillment of a vow, which could be eaten the day of, as well as the next day. The principles of gathering manna and the votive offering also parallel in this case. In regards to manna, the people could not rely on their own efforts for the Sabbath; no amount of work could feed them that day, God must be trusted that the previous days’ manna would not spoil. This is likewise true of the votive offering. Vows were made in cases where man trusted God to provide what he could not. An example of such an offering is that of Hannah in regards to the birth of her son, Samuel; she trusted God to provide her a son; such a thing was far outside the bounds of man’s ability. In fulfillment of her vow, she presented animals at the tabernacle after Samuel was born; this was a votive peace offering. As no effort of man could provide manna on the Sabbath, when there was none to collect, the votive offering was eaten on the day it was offered and the second day; signifying only something God could provide.</p>

<p>In regards to his death and resurrection, Jesus likewise appears to draw upon this concept of doing God’s work when appropriate as well as ceasing from labor in accordance with trusting God. Before healing the blind man in John 9 Jesus states, “We must work the work of Him who sent Me as long as it is day; night is coming when no one can work.” Throughout the book of John, Jesus often cryptically refers to his death, as is the case here.  It is no accident that the full day Jesus spent in the grave is the Sabbath, “when no one can work.” While the disciples trusted, obeyed and learned from Jesus when he was alive, the day he was in the grave no one had the ability to do anything, all they could do was trust in what Jesus had told them in the upper room. This corresponds both to eating previously gathered manna on the Sabbath as well as eating the meat of the votive peace offering on the second day.</p>

<p>But now we come to the third day of the peace offering, of gathering manna, and, most importantly, the day of Jesus’ resurrection. Here parallels end and beautiful contrasts begin. Manna could not sustain on the third day, it is not even mentioned; likewise, the meat of the peace offering must be burned to prevent decay, otherwise it would turn putrid. Instead, we turn to something greater, the peace offering of Jesus Christ; his body is true food, and his blood is real drink, the symbolism made clear in communion. On the third day, instead of rotting, God did not, as David states, let Jesus’ body see decay, but his body, the sacrifice, was renewed, resurrected. The communion meal is instead available for all time being able to be taken again and again for all eternity, offering real, permanent nourishment.</p>

<p>Christianity, Kierkegaard states, makes all things new; here, this concept is most literal. Remember, types of Christ not only demonstrate aspects of Christ and his atonement, but also Christ’s superiority to those types’ shortcomings.  It is no different here; with the image, the type, the shadow, the sacrificial meat becomes rotten on the third day. In Christ, the sacrifice not only does not decay, but raises again, renewed, putting on immortality. The contrast could not be greater.  We in turn can partake in the nourishment of Christ, symbolized in communion, again and again. Indeed, this is necessary, as Jesus tells his disciples they, the branches, must abide in him, the true vine; apart from him they, and us, can do nothing. The author of Hebrews likewise echoes such a concept, telling us Christ is “able to save forever those who draw near to God through Him, since He always lives to make intercession for them.” Christ’s nourishment sustains eternally, far past the second day of the peace offering.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The peace offering, or wholeness offering, was one of the sacrifices of the ancient Israelites. It represented fellowship with God and with one another, and should be considered the communion of the Old Testament. After an animal was slaughtered, the fat and entrails, simultaneously representing the best part of the animal and the seat of emotions of the offerer, were given to God by being burned on the bronze altar. The rest of the sacrifice, minus the priest’s share, could be eaten by the offerer with others, including his friends and family. In this way God and man were able to share something of a meal together, and the animal gave its life to physically sustain the offerer. While the parallel with communion and Jesus’ sacrifice for us are hopefully apparent, we’re here to elaborate on a little-discussed peculiarity of the peace offering, specifically as to when it could be eaten and the typology of this in particular.]]></summary></entry></feed>